[Music]
many things in life your health
insurance can often be confusing and
complicated
whether you've been insured for years or
you're new to the game
understanding your policy is important
to your health
and first you have to pay your premium
every month or your insurance could get
cancelled kind of like your cable
subscription
you can also think of it like a shared
healthcare piggy bank
we all chip in each month even if we're
healthy so the money is there when we
need it
if you get insurance at work your
employer probably pays most of your
premium
and the rest comes out of your paycheck
automatically
if you have medicaid you most likely
don't have to pay any premium at all
the federal government and your state
take care of that
if you're insured through a new health
insurance marketplace
depending on your income you may be
eligible for a tax credit that pays a
portion
of your premium once you have that shiny
new insurance card
you'll want to try really hard to keep
it in your wallet
to better your odds of staying healthy
be sure to take advantage of the free
preventive services that all new
insurance plans provide
but of course stuff
happens and that's when insurance really
comes in handy
now having insurance helps a lot but it
doesn't mean all your health care is
going to be free
there are lots of details about your
insurance plan that affect
how much you pay when you get sick or
injured
if you have medicaid a lot of these
services could very well be free
otherwise you'll likely have to pay
something when you go to the doctor or
fill a prescription
this is called a copay when it's a
specific dollar amount like 25 dollars
per visit
or coinsurance if it's a percentage of
the bill
there's also the deductible that's how
much comes out of your own pocket before
your insurance starts
paying depending on your plan you might
have a deductible for all your care
or it might only apply to some types of
care like hospital stays and
prescriptions
so read your plan material because it
could add up to thousands
of dollars another important part of
your plan
is the out-of-pocket maximum this is the
most you'll ever have to pay in any one
year
at least for the benefits your plan
covers your insurer will pay a hundred
percent
of anything beyond the maximum for the
rest of the year
it can be just as confusing dealing with
prescriptions
your plan has a list of drugs it will
pay for called a formulary
but the prices vary check with your
doctor or pharmacist because a generic
drug might fix you up the same as a
brand name drug
but the price difference could be huge
so those are the costs typically
involved but remember that they'll be
affected by your insurance plan's
provider network this is a list of
doctors and hospitals that are connected
to your plan
insurance companies negotiate discounts
with these providers
stay in network and the discounts get
passed to you
go out of network and you could end up
paying full price
and remember that out-of-pocket limit it
won't work if you go
out of network in some plans like hmos
or
epos your insurance would pay nothing if
you go
out of network in other plans like ppos
your insurance will cover you no matter
where you go but you'll pay a lot more
if you go
out of network also if you want to visit
a specialist like an orthopedist
some plans require a referral from your
primary care doctor
[Music]
sound easy enough well sometimes staying
in network
can be tricky in a hospital it's
possible that your surgeon could be in
network
while your anesthesiologist is not if
this happens to you
don't be afraid to negotiate with your
provider or file an appeal with your
insurer
so as you can see there's a lot to think
about when you choose an insurance plan
each year
some plans may have low premiums but
fewer doctors are hospitals and high
deductibles
there are trade-offs and understanding
and choosing among plans isn't always
easy remember if you have questions call
your health plan and ask
or check with your hospital or doctor if
you still have questions
your state insurance department or
consumer assistance program
can help with the affordable care act
there's new support for consumers
so take advantage of it having health
insurance protection
is a good thing especially when you know
how it works
we hope you're now better prepared for
the next time you have to pull that
insurance card
out of your wallet stay safe america
[Laughter]